script title the collateral damage a small business owner versus the machinery of trade war
total estimated length 20 minutes delivery pace measured contemplative narration with natural
pauses for reflection hook zero o'clock to zero 45 vertical bar approximately 45 seconds visual
atmosphere slow motion footage of cargo ships slicing through pacific fog at dawn cut to a single woman
in a virginia workshop stitching fabric by lamp light distant thunder of political speeches
in the long arc of civilizations empires do not fall with a single cataclysm they erode through
the quiet accumulation of decisions that seemed at the time entirely rational tonight we descend
not into the marble halls of Rome or the vanished courts of the Maya but into something more intimate
the collateral damage of great power competition this is the story of sarah wells a mother
an inventor an entrepreneur and how the invisible architecture of global trade suddenly
turned against the very people it was meant to serve background and the unfolding of systemic
fragility 3045 to eight o'clock vertical bar approximately seven minutes 15 seconds visual
atmosphere archival style reenactments kitchen table in 2012 with baby gear factory floors in
china loading docks in 2025 congressional hearing room intercut with graphs of tariff
escalations and supply chain maps glowing red sarah wells began in the most ordinary of places
her own kitchen in fairfax county virginia like so many founders before her she saw a gap no one
else had filled working mothers needed a better way to carry breast pumps bottles ice packs
dignity and function in one elegant bag in 2012 she started stitching prototypes by the mid minus
2010s sarah wells bags had found its rhythm innovative design in america precision manufacturing
in china where entire ecosystems of skilled labor specialized materials and ruthless efficiency
had coalesced over decades for years the system worked with deceptive smoothness containers crossed
to the pacific margins held american mothers received thoughtfully designed products at prices
they could afford the complexity remained hidden like the root systems beneath a thriving forest
then in early 2025 the winds shifted as geopolitical tensions hardened into policy
tariffs on chinese imports climbed first one layer then another sarah s shipment was already at sea
when the second round hit by the time the containers reached port her clearing costs
had ballooned by 17 000 on a single order cumulative duties reached levels approaching 54
to 62 percent she faced an impossible trinity raise prices and lose loyal customers already
stretched by inflation absorb the costs and bleed cash or attempt reshoring only to discover that
american manufacturing capacity for her specialized components simply did not exist at scale
role materials even for american made assembly still traced back through chinese supply chains
the cost multiplier three to four times this was not failure of nerve or innovation it was the
sudden revelation of institutional fragility the brittle interdependence built into just
in time global systems small businesses which employ nearly half of american workers
operate with thin margins and limited buffers large corporations can hedge currencies
renegotiate contracts absorb shocks or pass costs downstream the sarah wells of the economy
cannot across 2025 business bankruptcies climbed toward 15 year highs cash flow crises rippled
through retail manufacturing and services what looked on spreadsheets like necessary medicine
for national security revealed itself on the ground as a wealth transfer mechanism from small
scale creators and their communities upward toward those with scale capital and political access
history offers echoes the smooth holly tariff act of 1930 was passed with similar intentions
to shield american farmers and industry amid economic pain instead retaliatory tariffs
collapsed global trade by two-thirds within years what began as protection became mutual
impoverishment the intricate web of commerce once severed does not heal quickly supply
chains are not mere logistics they are living ecologies of trust skill and incremental knowledge
that take generations to grow and moments to disrupt surviving assets and irreducible value
it eight o'clock to 13 o'clock vertical bar approximately five minutes visual atmosphere
close-ups of hands working stitching sketching customer emails archival footage of resilient
small-town businesses through past crises subtle data visualizations showing adaptive
small firms script title the collateral damage a small business owner versus the machinery of
trade war total estimated length 20 minutes delivery pace measured contemplative narration
with natural pauses for reflection hook zero o'clock to 045 vertical bar approximately 45
seconds visual atmosphere slow motion footage of cargo ships slicing through pacific fog at dawn
cut to a single woman in a virginia workshop stitching fabric by lamp light distant thunder
of political speeches in the long arc of civilizations empires do not fall with a single
cataclysm they erode through the quiet accumulation of decisions that seemed at the time entirely
rational tonight we descend not into the marble halls of Rome or the vanished courts of the
Maya but into something more intimate the collateral damage of great power competition
this is the story of Sarah Wells a mother an inventor an entrepreneur and how the invisible
architecture of global trade suddenly turned against the very people it was meant to serve
background and the unfolding of systemic fragility 3045 to eight o'clock vertical bar
approximate lesia in minutes 15 seconds visual atmosphere archival style reenactments
kitchen table in 2012 with baby gear factory floors in china loading docks in 2025 congressional
hearing room intercut with graphs of tariff escalations and supply chain maps glowing red
sarah wells began in the most ordinary of places her own kitchen in fairfax county virginia
like so many founders before her she saw a gap no one else had filled working mothers needed a
better way to carry breast pumps bottles ice packs dignity and function in one elegant bag
in 2012 she started stitching prototypes by the mid-2010s sarah wells bags had found its rhythm
innovative design in america precision manufacturing in china where entire ecosystems of skilled
labor specialized materials and ruthless efficiency had coalesced over decades for years the system
worked with deceptive smoothness containers crossed to the pacific margins held american
mothers received thoughtfully designed products at prices they could afford the complexity
remained hidden like the root systems beneath a thriving forest then in early 2025 the winds
shifted as geopolitical tensions hardened into policy tariffs on chinese imports climbed first
one layer then another sarah s shipment was already at sea when the second round hit by the time the
containers reached port her clearing costs had ballooned by 17 000 on a single order cumulative
duties reached levels approaching 54 to 62 percent she faced an impossible trinity raise prices and lose
loyal customers already stretched by inflation absorb the costs and bleed cash or attempt
reshoring only to discover that american manufacturing capacity for her specialized components
simply did not exist at scale roll materials even for american made assembly still traced back
through chinese supply chains the cost multiplier three to four times this was not failure of nerve
or innovation it was the sudden revelation of institutional fragility the brittle interdependence
built into just in time global systems small businesses which employ nearly half of american
workers operate with thin margins and limited buffers large corporations can hedge currencies
renegotiate contracts absorb shocks or pass costs downstream the sarah wells of the economy
cannot across 2025 business bankruptcies climbed toward 15-year highs cash flow crises rippled
through retail manufacturing and services what looked on spreadsheets like necessary medicine
for national security revealed itself on the ground as a wealth transfer mechanism
from small scale creators and their communities upward toward those with scale capital and
political access history offers echoes the smooth holly tariff act of 1930 was passed with similar
intentions to shield american farmers and industry amid economic pain instead retaliatory
tariffs collapsed global trade by two thirds within years what began as protection became
mutual impoverishment the intricate web of commerce once severed does not heal quickly supply chains
are not mere logistics they are living ecologies of trust skill and incremental knowledge that
take generations to grow and moments to disrupt surviving assets and irreducible value it
eight o'clock to 13 o'clock vertical bar approximately five minutes visual atmosphere
close-ups of hands working stitching sketching customer emails archival footage of resilient
small-town businesses through past crises subtle data visualizations showing adaptive small firms