script title the collateral damage a small business owner versus the machinery of trade war
total estimated length 20 minutes delivery pace measured contemplative narration with natural
pauses for reflection hook zero o'clock to zero 45 vertical bar approximately 45 seconds visual
atmosphere slow motion footage of cargo ships slicing through pacific fog at dawn cut to a single woman
in a virginia workshop stitching fabric by lamp light distant thunder of political speeches
in the long arc of civilizations empires do not fall with a single cataclysm they erode
through the quiet accumulation of decisions that seemed at the time entirely rational tonight
we descend not into the marble halls of rome or the vanished courts of the maya but into something
more intimate the collateral damage of great power competition this is the story of sarah wells
a mother an inventor an entrepreneur and how the invisible architecture of global trade
suddenly turned against the very people it was meant to serve background and the unfolding of systemic
fragility 3045 to eight o'clock vertical bar approximate lesia and minutes 15 seconds visual
atmosphere archival style reenactments kitchen table in 2012 with baby gear factory floors in
china loading docks in 2025 congressional hearing room intercut with graphs of tariff
escalations and supply chain maps glowing red sarah wells began in the most ordinary of places
her own kitchen in fairfax county virginia like so many founders before her she saw a gap no
one else had filled working mothers needed a better way to carry breast pumps bottles
ice packs dignity and function in one elegant bag in 2012 she started stitching prototypes
by the mid 2010s sarah wells bags had found its rhythm innovative design in america
precision manufacturing in china where entire ecosystems of skilled labor specialized materials
and ruthless efficiency had coalesced over decades for years the system worked with
deceptive smoothness containers crossed to the pacific margins held american mothers
received thoughtfully designed products at prices they could afford the complexity remained hidden
like the root systems beneath a thriving forest then in early 2025 the winds shifted as geopolitical
tensions hardened into policy tariffs on chinese imports climbed first one layer then another
sarah s shipment was already at sea when the second round hit by the time the containers
reached port her clearing costs had ballooned by 17 000 on a single order cumulative duties
reached levels approaching 54 to 62 percent she faced an impossible trinity raise prices and
lose loyal customers already stretched by inflation absorb the costs and bleed cash
or attempt reshoring only to discover that american manufacturing capacity for her specialized
components simply did not exist at scale role materials even for american made assembly
still traced back through chinese supply chains the cost multiplier three to four times
this was not failure of nerve or innovation it was the sudden revelation of institutional
fragility the brittle interdependence built into just in time global systems small businesses
which employ nearly half of american workers operate with thin margins and limited buffers
large corporations can hedge currencies renegotiate contracts absorb shocks or pass
costs downstream the sarah wells of the economy cannot across 2025 business bankruptcies
climbed toward 15-year highs cash flow crises rippled through retail manufacturing
and services what looked on spreadsheets like necessary medicine for national security
revealed itself on the ground as a wealth transfer mechanism from small-scale creators
and their communities upward toward those with scale capital and political access history
offers echoes the smooth holly tariff act of 1930 was passed with similar intentions
to shield american farmers and industry amid economic pain instead retaliatory tariffs
collapsed global trade by two-thirds within years what began as protection became mutual
impoverishment the intricate web of commerce once severed does not heal quickly supply
chains are not mere logistics they are living ecologies of trust skill and incremental knowledge
that take generations to grow and moments to disrupt surviving assets and irreducible value
it eight o'clock to 13 o'clock vertical bar approximately five minutes visual atmosphere
close-ups of hands working stitching sketching customer emails archival footage of resilient
small-town businesses through past crises subtle data visualizations showing adaptive small firms