Script Title: The Collateral Damage — A Small Business Owner vs. the Machinery of Trade War
Total Estimated Length: 20 minutes Delivery Pace: Measured, contemplative narration with natural
pauses for reflection. Hook 0:00 to 0:45 | approximately 45 seconds Visual
Atmosphere: Slow-motion footage of cargo ships slicing through Pacific fog at dawn. Cut to a single woman
in a Virginia workshop, stitching fabric by lamplight. Distant thunder of political speeches.
In the long arc of civilizations, empires do not fall with a single cataclysm. They erode
through the quiet accumulation of decisions that seemed, at the time, entirely rational. Tonight
we descend not into the marble halls of Rome or the vanished courts of the Maya, but into something
more intimate: the collateral damage of great-power competition. This is the story of Sarah Wells —
a mother, an inventor, an entrepreneur — and how the invisible architecture of global trade
suddenly turned against the very people it was meant to serve.
Background & The Unfolding of Systemic Fragility 0:45 to 8:00 | approximately 7 minutes 15 seconds Visual
Atmosphere: Archival-style reenactments: kitchen table in 2012 with baby gear; factory floors in
China; loading docks in 2025; congressional hearing room. Intercut with graphs of tariff
escalations and supply chain maps glowing red. Sarah Wells began in the most ordinary of places
her own kitchen in Fairfax County, Virginia. Like so many founders before her, she saw a gap no
one else had filled. Working mothers needed a better way to carry breast pumps, bottles,
ice packs — dignity and function in one elegant bag. In 2012 she started stitching prototypes.
By the mid-2010s, Sarah Wells Bags had found its rhythm: innovative design in America,
precision manufacturing in China, where entire ecosystems of skilled labor, specialized materials,
and ruthless efficiency had coalesced over decades. For years the system worked with
deceptive smoothness. Containers crossed the Pacific. Margins held. American mothers
received thoughtfully designed products at prices they could afford. The complexity remained hidden,
like the root systems beneath a thriving forest. Then, in early 2025, the winds shifted as geopolitical
tensions hardened into policy. Tariffs on Chinese imports climbed — first one layer, then another.
Sarah's shipment was already at sea when the second round hit. By the time the containers
reached port, her clearing costs had ballooned by $15,000 on a single order. Cumulative duties
reached levels approaching 54 to 62 percent. She faced an impossible trinity: raise prices and
lose loyal customers already stretched by inflation; absorb the costs and bleed cash;
or attempt reshoring, only to discover that American manufacturing capacity for her specialized
components simply did not exist at scale. Raw materials, even for "American-made" assembly,
still traced back through Chinese supply chains. The cost multiplier: three to four times.
This was not failure of nerve or innovation. It was the sudden revelation of institutional
fragility — the brittle interdependence built into just-in-time global systems. Small businesses,
which employ nearly half of American workers, operate with thin margins and limited buffers.
Large corporations can hedge currencies, renegotiate contracts, absorb shocks, or pass
costs downstream. The Sarah Wellses of the economy cannot. Across 2025, business bankruptcies
climbed toward fifteen-year highs. Cash-flow crises rippled through retail, manufacturing,
and services. What looked on spreadsheets like necessary medicine for national security
revealed itself on the ground as a wealth transfer mechanism from small-scale creators
and their communities upward toward those with scale, capital, and political access. History
offers echoes. The Smoot-Hawley Tariff Act of 1930 was passed with similar intentions
to shield American farmers and industry amid economic pain. Instead, retaliatory tariffs
collapsed global trade by two-thirds within years. What began as protection became mutual
impoverishment. The intricate web of commerce once severed does not heal quickly. Supply
chains are not mere logistics; they are living ecologies of trust, skill, and incremental knowledge
that take generations to grow and moments to disrupt.
Surviving Assets & Irreducible Value 8:00 to 13:00 | approximately 5 minutes Visual Atmosphere:
Close-ups of hands working — stitching, sketching, customer emails. Archival footage of resilient
small-town businesses through past crises. Subtle data visualizations showing adaptive small firms.